so now let's try to apply the idea of
pipelining to a processor in a
traditional processor that is nowadays
too simple so we only use it to teach
students but it still shows how things
work we have a program counter we use
the program counter to access the
instruction memory we get the
instruction from there we look at the
instruction to decode it to figure out
which type of instruction it is
meanwhile we could be reading our
registers once we have read our
registers we can feed them to the A
where we're going to do the add or
subtract or an exor or whatever the
instruction wants us to do the decoding
logic is going to tell the what to do
once we get the result of the AL we
could be done and just write the result
of the register or we could have a load
or a store instruction in which case
what the ALU computed is really the
address that we used to access our data
memory and what comes out of data memory
is what we end up writing to our
registers and then of course there is
stuff to do with branches and so on but
basically we can do one instruction per
cycle by starting at the PC fetching the
instruction accessing the registers
doing the operation accessing the data
memory and then writing the result back
to registers so you can see that the
instruction kind of goes through these
five phases we fetch the instruction we
read registers and the code we use the
ALU we access the memory and finally we
write the registers the time to do this
might be something something like 20 NS
so now we can do one instruction every
20 nond so how do we apply pipelining to
this well the idea is that if here we
have our fetch the code ALU memory and
right part of this processor and here we
show what happens in cycle one we will
fetch some instruction i1 in cycle two
instruction i1 moves to the code in
cycle C3 instruction i1 will be doing
the ALU operation in cycle C4 i1 will
move to do memory and then in cycle C5
i1 will write the result and next cycle
we can begin the instruction two if we
do that then we really will finish one
instruction every 20 NS if we apply the
idea of pipelining here in cycle one we
are still fetching instruction i1 in
cycle two we will be decoding
instruction i1 but we can begin fetching
the instruction I2 when instruction i1
move to do the Alo operation I2 can move
to be decoded and I3 can be fetched in
the fourth cycle i1 is the memory stage
I2 will be doing the AL operation I3
will be here being decoded and I4 will
be fetched and then when i1 is in the
last part of the pipeline I2 will be
right after after it in the memory stage
I3 will be doing the AL operation I4
will be decoded and we will be fetching
an instruction I5 so now the idea is
that once the i1 leaves the pipeline
very soon after that I2 will leave the
pipeline if we divide this 20 nond into
five equal pieces for these stages each
stage will be four NS and now the
latency to do i1 is still 20 NS so it
takes 20 NS to do instruction but the
throughput will be one instruction will
finish every 4 NS cuz once i1 leaves
that's how long it takes for I2 to leave
and then we just keep pouring
instructions out so it's similar to the
oil pipeline it takes a while to fill
the pipeline but once we do instructions
keep pouring out at a very high rate